Hello and welcome back to
another video with ItsDrDan.
And today we're gonna look further into
introductory chemistry, specifically
math skills to help you ACE chemistry.
This video we're gonna be looking at
dimensional analysis, which is a follow-up
video to my unit conversion video.
So, it helps you be able to
see a lot tougher problems.
They're gonna commonly come
across, whether it's at the very
beginning unit, conversions, or
when you get the stoichiometry.
This is one of the most fundamental
skills that you can have, or
chemistry, physics, even engineering
classes that you'll come across.
So, for this particular one, the
whole idea with dimensional analysis
is that it's a mathematical method
to convert measured units into
units needed to answer problems.
Which is a little bit of a mouthful,
but it comes down to trying to answer
a lot of word problems, which when
we come across those, they can be
really overwhelming when you see them.
You can freeze up, you
see all these words.
You don't know how to find important
pieces of information, possibly.
And a lot of that comes from middle
school and high school, where maybe
you were never coming across all
the skills to do that, or maybe
you have, and that's even better.
But, if you haven't, I'm gonna go through
a lot of those tips to show you how can
you go through a word problem, how do
you decipher it so that way you can find
the conversion factors needed to answer
these problems, which all conversion
factor is, is a ratio or a relationship
that's being hidden in a word problem.
So, you're gonna be looking for
numbers, little keywords I'm gonna
show you look for, to give you all
those little tips and hints to be
able to do dimensional analysis.
So, just look at a little preview,
like what does that exactly mean when
it comes to dimensional analysis?
Well, we're gonna be looking at just
understanding simple fractions, right?
We set up before in unit conversions
was we set up a T table, like the
one at the bottom of the screen and
put down like the one right here.
So if I was, you always write
down your different units you
were given and what you desire.
So if I'm given A and I desire
C, I might have a couple
relationships that can get me there.
Whether it's through prefixes US to
metric conversions, maybe density might
be even something that's given to you
in a problem through maybe medical
doses, dosages, there's all kinds
of things that you can come across.
So how does this exactly work?
Well, let's say if I'm given A, you always
try to start with a number by itself.
Then what we are going to do is cancel
out those units, right when they are
opposites of each other, they can cancel.
So opposites cancel each other out.
And that is the key thing that
we're always looking for canceling.
So when those cancels, right, being
that A is equivalent to B, we can
write that relationship and we
can also continue to relate the
relationship that B is equivalent to C.
So, what happens here
is unit cancellation.
A units would cancel A units, right?
And that's what the
highlighting here represents.
And then the same thing here is that,
okay, B units cancel out B units and
then that would leave us only with C.
And that's the key.
We're trying to cancel all of
our different units as we're
going through these problems.
So we're gonna go through a bunch of
different tips and a bunch of examples in
this video, and I hope that this helps.
All right, let's get into it.
Let's go through tips on how
to decipher word problems.
So starting here, whenever you
see a word problem, it can feel
like an extremely big puzzle.
And it can be extremely confusing
for a lot of new chemistry students.
But the thing is, that's all it is,
is a puzzle, meaning there's only
one way that it can fit together.
The pieces fit a specific way.
Meaning that our units are
going to cancel a specific way.
So when we are going through these a few
tips, we wanna read the problems slowly.
Every single word could hold a clue.
We wanna be always looking through our
little magnifying glass to find that clue.
Try to read the problem
multiple times if you have to.
There's sometimes on exam, yes, there's
a time limit, but when you're doing
your homework, or maybe if you have
a quiz that's not timed, Spend that
time to learn how to do problems.
It's a study method.
The more you do, the easier it will get.
It just takes practice.
We need to practice anything, right?
It's like I tell students all the time, if
you played a sport or did an instrument,
or maybe if you game, or if you do really
any hobby when you first did it, you
probably were not as good at it first.
That's normal, right?
We're human, we learn.
So as you got better, you improved.
It's the same thing in  chem.
It takes time, and that's
really discouraging.
It does take time.
That's with any subject.
That's the idea of learning, right?
The more you do it, the
better you will get.
So trust me, it will get better.
So when you read it multiple times, what
you need to do is define your givens.
So what information is in
the problem that you have?
So numbers that you already start with.
And write your desired, which
means what are you trying to find?
It's usually a unit or a specific answer
that will be set out in the problem.
The last thing is you wanna
look for conversion factors,
but for a lot of us, how?
How do we do that?
Well, there's gonna be key words
we're gonna be looking for and when,
with those key words, the whole idea
here is that it's gonna help you
let the units guide your thinking.
Meaning they need to cancel out.
So top and bottom of these
fractions, they cancel.
So we need to try to map
out a path for ourselves.
So, and that's what we're gonna be
doing as we go through these problems.
So let's take a look at some of
the different terms that we will
come across to in these problems.
That can be a hint for
your conversion factors.
Okay, so when we want to see the
world through conversion factors,
there are giveaway phrases
in a lot of these problems.
So, think of some things that come in in
your everyday life if I ask you, okay.
The following phrases, if you see
in each, well, if I ask you for a
dollar and I ask you to make change,
well, one thing that you could do
is, oh, alright, there's a hundred
pennies in every or in each dollar.
Well, Knowing that that is a conversion
term that we can write for ourselves.
So if you have a hundred pennies
in a dollar, we can define
that conversion term, right?
And you can either write that
on top or bottom, depending
on how you need to do that.
If I ask you how many days are
in there in a week and right away
you're like, seven, of course.
Well, you just define a conversion
term without me doing anything.
It's second nature 'cause you
practice it your entire life.
So per, if you see something per
something that's telling you another
one, so seven days a week, we can
define that as a fraction for ourselves.
Seven days for every week.
And you can flip it, right if you need to.
You can do it one way or the other,
depending on how you need your to units
cancel if you see in
every, well, all right.
If I ask you how many
months are in every year?
Well, there's 12 months in every year.
If I ask, we can even
define a term, right?
So if I say there's 2000 nails
in every barn that's being built,
that's defining your own term.
It doesn't have to be this preset thing.
You can define it any problem,
can define it however you need.
Or if I ask you for recipes, right?
Recipes are ratios.
Whether you need one cup of milk.
In this recipe.
So you could say, alright, well
one cup of milk and oh, spelled
milk wrong in the recipe.
Right?
That could be a conversion term.
Or if I say 12 eggs in a
dozen is a conversion term.
All of these can be defined
using these keywords.
So write them down for yourself.
Try to train your brain to finding them.
They will help you.
So there's three examples that
we have in this video for you.
We'll go through them.
We're going to find all
the key information.
So find our givens, find our desires, and
we're gonna find the unit conversions.
So feel free to spend that time and pause
when we are, when I read through the
problem before I start solving it all.
Or you can just watch it, but try
to, try to see if you can do it too.
Try to work along with me and
it will help you learn it.
Alright, so let's go on
to our first problem.
Our first problem of the video.
So for this problem, what we are asking
is how many minutes will it take to
drive to Los Angeles from San Francisco?
If an average speed of 72 miles per
hour is maintained, the distance
between the two cities is 405 miles.
You're like, wait, what?
I thought this was a chemistry.
Well, being able to read a word
problem is still chemistry.
Even when we do chemical equations later.
We need to be able to find
key piece of information.
So let's go through it.
So I read that fast, so spend the time
to read it to yourself fully if needed.
So the first sentence, how many minutes?
There's your, that's
your desired right there.
How many minutes?
So what we're gonna do is we're going
to highlight that and we are gonna
write down here are desired, so desired.
Is minutes.
Okay.
So it's in the first line.
It's not always in the last line.
Sometimes it's earlier or
it's earlier than that.
Alright.
And it's asking from LA to San Francisco,
that's, that doesn't matter, right?
That's just, that's just information
and a lot of these problems, it just
gives you information to distract you.
And that's something that's very common,
especially in standardized tests.
If you're a nursing student and you
might have to take the TEAS test one
day, very common, they might give you a
different test that will distract you.
So, and then it says, if you have an
average speed of 72 miles per hour,
all right, that's a conversion term.
We can see the word per here.
Okay.
Which meant that, alright, well
I have 72 miles for every hour.
That is a conversion for
ourselves that we can define.
So when we go through that, we
can write 72 miles per hour.
Then we have a ratio
and that can be flipped.
Don't forget that, right?
So we can also write one hour
over 72 miles as we continue
to write, read the problem.
It says the distance between
the city is 405 miles.
We'll write that down too.
So we also have 405 miles in the problem.
So we're looking for all these
little details that we have here.
They will help us find it.
So we need to see what
is our commonality here?
What do we have?
Well, we want minutes.
We have a time factor, which is hours.
That's gonna be our bridge there.
So let's also set up the problem
for ourselves with all these, right?
We will set this up as
a T table for ourselves.
'cause it shows fractions.
It makes it a lot easier
to keep yourself organized.
Now in these problems, we are
given two different types of
things that we can start with.
We have con conversion factors, which
are both, which are these fractions
up here, and then we also have a term
by itself, you, if you have it, which
should most of these word problems.
You will.
You always want to start with the term
by itself, and I can't say that enough.
Start with the term by itself.
The reason is is because you
can't flip it easily, right?
It's something that, sure, you could
do it at the end of the problem.
But at the beginning, you there,
it has to be in the numerator,
cancel units and all these problems.
So if you have one, try to always
start with the term by itself.
It should lead to the correct answer as
long as you cancel your units correctly.
So, okay, we have 405 miles.
Now how do we cancel out miles?
Well, I had two different
terms up top that I could use.
I have the one on the left.
And then I have the one on the right.
And both these are like puzzle
pieces that you can fit into
your puzzle a very specific way.
Because units, right, they need to be
opposite of each other to cancel, right?
They need to be opposite.
So in this case, if I have
miles on top in my T table, we
also need miles on the bottom.
So we're right 72 miles per hour.
And that will cancel, right?
So you can see how their opposites.
Opposites always cancel.
And we'll highlight it so that we
can show how that's canceling, right?
Opposites cancel each other out.
And that's the ultimate thing, right?
When we see these opposite units,
they will cancel each other.
So now we have hours.
How do we get to minutes?
Well, how many minutes are an hour?
You tell, you look at
the timer all the time.
Right?
When you're in class, you're like, oh
my god, time's not going fast enough.
So, but you know, 60 minutes is in one
hour, so how do you cancel out an hour?
With another hour?
So we'd write one hour on the bottom
and then we'll write 60 minutes on
top and then we can see, alright,
well once again, my unit's canceling.
Fantastic.
This is great.
Now we have our final unit,
which is what we wanted.
We wanted minutes so we can give
a little check to make sure.
Okay, we're good.
So now we can do the math.
So when you're doing these, remember each
one of these is like a little fraction.
Each of these little blocks that
are here, it's like a fraction.
So what we're doing is we'll
take that 405, divide it by 72.
It equals times by 60, hit
equal on your calculator.
Now when you get that answer,
You're gonna get 337.5 minutes.
Now, is that the correct answer?
The quick answer is no.
So we need to round it sig
figs  matter, because these are
revolving around measurement.
Measurement is key in science.
So being that we had 405
miles and 72 miles per hour,
those are measurements, right?
You look at your speed gauge, you
do that with with a speedometer.
That is a measurement tool.
So how many sig figs do we have?
We have two sig figs and then we measure
the distance, whether it's with your
G P S or a map that is three sig figs.
Those are measurements.
So what was the lower of the two?
Because it's all multiplication.
Division would be two.
So when we round this to two sig figs,
it would be 340 minutes would be our
final answer, and we box that off.
You did the first word problem possibly.
Let's now go to another example.
All right, our second example, this is
for all the health scientists out there.
So dosages and medicine is a common thing
that you will have to calculate on the
go, potentially in your future career.
So even if you're not, and you're just
interested in chem, or just you wanna
pass the class or any class, we still
have to be able to read these problems.
So with this one, it says,
many medications have dosages
that depend on weight.
The dosage of naproxen is five
milligrams per kilogram of
body weight, two times per day.
If 120 pound patient starts with
a 6,000 milligram bottle, how
many days will the bottle last?
Oh, that sounds hard
and it's really scary.
So let's look through it.
So the first sentence, many medications
have a doses that depend on weight.
Great.
It's a piece of just information.
It doesn't tell you anything.
So just something that's useful to know.
Um, but not good for this problem.
The dosage of naproxen is five
milligrams per that word, per right.
That's gonna come up a lot.
Kilogram of body weight, I
think I make a different color.
Let's see, some brighter five
milligrams per kilogram, and
that says two times per day.
That is a very complex, uh,
conversion, so let's write that down.
So it says five milligrams per kilogram.
Five milligrams per of the drug.
So we'll put five milligrams of
drug per kilogram of body weight.
And what we are doing is we're
doing that two times per day.
We'll put that as like a times two.
And the whole idea with that is this
is a unit that you gotta mash together
and derive for yourself it looks like.
So we're gonna have to potentially
use this to derive something.
So this is gonna be a multi-step problem.
Whenever you see something that complex.
Now it says that if 120 pound
patient, okay, so that's another
big piece of information.
So 120 pounds.
So let's write that down.
Hundred 20 pound.
And that's for body weight.
So there's a conversion
term that will cancel.
Eventually it's body weight
and body weight will cancel.
But we need to get them in the same units.
That's crucial.
Let me move that over just a little
'cause it can't cut off by me.
There we go.
Now it says the patient starts
with a 6,000 milligram bottle.
Okay, so here is another piece.
So of the drug.
So we have 6,000 milligram of the drug.
Okay?
How many days will the bottle last?
Oof, how many days will the bottle last?
So what our desire, so we have
a lot of given information, all
given are desired on the other end.
Just, we wanna know how many days
will, will the drug last us before
we have to refill our prescription.
So if we are doing that, well,
let's see where to start.
There's multiple possibilities here.
One thing you'll see is that there
are, there's one giant conversion
term, the five milligrams of the
drug per kilogram of body weight.
A massive conversion.
I would not start with that.
Then we have 120 pounds.
Okay.
And then the 600 milligrams of
the drug itself, or 6,000, sorry.
So one of those two terms we have to
start with, body weight is usually
an easier one to start with 'cause
then it gets those units canceled.
Um, and I think what we'll do is
this, we'll do this in two steps.
So let's start with body weight.
So with this we have 120 pound.
Patient, right.
So that, I'm gonna put body above it
just so we're, we're familiar with
where that weight is coming from.
'cause notice we have two masses, so
we need to make sure that, that the
masses that are together stay together.
Um, in terms of cancellation, we
don't wanna mix the milligrams with
the pounds and kilograms, even though
they're all masses, but they're
not related to the same thing.
So we now gotta go from
pounds to kilograms.
That way we can use the
one conversion term.
So we have to look in our handy
dandy sheets to see, okay.
Pounds to kilograms or reference sheets.
And you will see that 2.205
pounds is one kilogram.
So this is something you gotta,
you look up when we do that.
Pounds cancels pounds, it puts
in in kilogram for ourselves.
The next thing that we're gonna do
is now we can use that big conversion
term, which when we combine this.
We can essentially figure out how much
drug are we taking per day, per kilogram.
So what I mean by that is let's
combine that all together.
So if I take five milligrams times
it by two, what that will then
tell us is that, okay, well we're
taking 10 milligrams of the drug.
Uh, for every one kilogram per day, the
one kilogram of body weight, one kg.
Of body weight per day.
Okay, so now when that
happens, this is a hard one.
It's trying to see that as a body weight.
The kilogram of body weight will
cancel the kilogram of body weight.
They'll both cancel.
And now this leaves us with
10 milligrams of drug per day.
So, which is what we, we
eventually need to get today's.
So let's just solve for this
part, and it will define for
ourselves a milligram per day.
Conversion term, which is great.
That's something we'll help us do.
Figure out the bottle.
How long will the bottle last?
That'll be our last little tea table.
So what we need to do is 120 divided
by 2.205 times 10, and what we will
get is 544 milligrams per day, is
what our patient needs to take.
Great.
So now what we will now
do is one last step.
Which is that we'll have 6,000
milligram bottle and we will convert
that using this dosage, which is the
544 milligrams for every day, and
that will give us our final answer.
So we do 6,000 divided by 5 44,
and what we're going to get is 11.0
days is gonna be our final answer.
So it's gonna last the patient 11
days before they need to either
get the prescription refilled or
that will be how long it will last.
So this kit is a harder problem
'cause it took multiple steps.
But notice that being that we had
two separate terms by themselves,
the 6,000 and the one 20, I split
it up into two problems to make it
easier, try to simplify the problem.
If it's something really big and
you, and you can't really see how
to cancel everything out easily, it
could be split into two problems.
Just start eliminating a few
units and then try to come, come
back together on the next part.
The third example would
be a little bit easier.
I wanted to do one hard one.
Alright, onto the next problem.
So, at a local college, the students
have been overdosing on caffeine
to help them study for exams.
Oh, no, that's not good.
But that did not give us any
piece of information that
we needed for this problem.
It just told us the situation, meaning
many students have been getting
sick from drinking too much coffee.
It is known that three gram grams of
caffeine taking in one day is dangerous.
Okay, so right there we
have the number three grams.
So maybe that might be a very
important piece of information.
So let's highlight it now.
It says How many cups of coffee
would be too much and at a
dangerous level of three grams.
Okay, so there's that
three gram number again.
So that's definitely gonna be an
important piece of information that
we need to write down, that we need
know something about three grams.
That is our limit.
So three grams of coffee.
Now it says a cup of coffee contains
21.5 milligrams of caffeine per ounce.
Okay, so that means that we have
another conversion term, which is,
that's 21.5 milligrams per ounce.
Let's write that down for ourselves too.
So we have 21.5 milligrams of caffeine.
Per ounce.
Okay, so there's that per term, right?
We keep seeing that.
So that's one.
And then the last thing, it says
a cup contains eight ounces.
Oh, great.
So it says something we don't have to look
up is a cup contains eight ounces, so it
tells you how big is a cup of coffee cup.
And that's eight ounces.
Great.
So now when we do this, let's
see what our common trend is.
So what should we start with?
We have two fractions, right?
So we have two conversion terms.
We have the, the 21.5 milligrams
and the one cup for eight ounces.
We have a term by itself, so we
should definitely start with that.
That will make our problem easier.
However, how do we bridge the, the gut
or the gap from coffee, which is grams?
Or or how much, sorry,
it's not even coffee.
That's actually caffeine.
Three grams of caffeine.
It's not three grams of coffee.
Uh, how would we bridge that gap?
Well, being that two of these things
are both caffeine, we're gonna have
to go from caffeine to caffeine.
That's our key.
So we need to go from grams to milligrams.
So why don't we define that for ourselves.
Now, you can look it up in our
handy dandy prefix tables, but
I will write it down for us.
One gram.
It's 1000 milligrams.
So we have another conversion
term for ourselves.
So we can choose whichever
one will help us later.
So when we start this down, uh,
what we're gonna start with is
the term that is by itself, which
is a three grams of caffeine.
We have three grams and that's caffeine.
Then we will com use the mil.
We will convert that to
milligrams for ourselves.
So what we said was one
gram is a thousand mg.
And then we see, alright,
that canceled out.
Great.
Now what we will do is use that
conversion term that was up top, right?
So the 21.5 uh, milligrams,
we're gonna use that one there.
So when we use that, The 21.5 milligrams
will cancel out two things here.
So look at this just to see for when
you do stoichiometry, this is useful.
So the milligrams cancels the milligrams.
And then the word caffeine will
cancel the labeling for caffeine.
So all gets canceled.
You can do that where you can
cancel it in multiple places
as long as it's all top bottom.
So keep that in mind.
And they do not have to
be next to each other.
You can cancel across a problem, which
is really, really useful skill to know.
Alright, and that's for every ounce.
And I'll, I'm gonna shorten
that for ounce, right?
So it's, Oz is an ounce.
So now the last step.
For this type of problem is
that eight ounces is per cup.
So we have eight ounces is one cup,
and let me move all this a little over.
So when we do that right, we'll see
the ounces, we'll cancel ounces,
then we'll be left with cups.
So we'll multiply everything
on top and then we'll divide
by the things on the bottom.
So we have three times 1000.
It equals divide by 21.5.
It equals.
And divide by eight when you do that.
Right.
This problem has to be in three
sig figs based on the numbers given
to us in the beginning, and what
we will get is 17.4 cups of coffee
with lead to a student getting sick.
That's a lot of coffee.
Hopefully you're not drinking that much
in a day during your semesters or at work.
Um, but 17.4.
All right.
That's how you do these hard word
problems with our final takeaways.
What we are gonna be doing in
these different problems is
we are always looking for the
given pieces of information.
We look for sentences with two
quantities or conversions, so we can
write down all these little givens.
You'll then have to map out how
to go from one unit to the other.
This might require prefixes.
Those are a big hint if
you see similar units.
Same thing going from us to metric.
We might see the same thing to pay
attention to your measurements.
Are they all masses?
Are they all volumes?
Are they length?
Are they the same?
They will help you.
If you need to read the problem
slowly to find what you need, don't
feel like if you read it once,
you're like, oh, I didn't find it.
Go word by word.
When I say problems, I say
them out loud all the time.
If you're sitting at your desk, you
can say it to yourself just quietly.
If that helps you do it, don't
worry about the people next to you.
Unless your teacher starts
yelling at you, that's different.
But if you need to kind of
word it to yourself, do it.
Help yourself.
Uh, let those units guide you
in your thinking because those
comment units, they'll, they'll,
they'll all have to cancel, right?
Opposites cancel.
Look for those.
Now, the last tip is don't
start with a conversion.
That's not all the time.
There are exceptions to that.
If you were given a problem
with only conversion factors,
then okay, you have no choice.
If that's the case, The hint I
can give you is make sure the
unit that you desire is on top.
Okay?
So you want it on top, so that way
on the final part of the problem,
it's still up there so you can
just cancel the other units out.
So start with whatever you want, where
it needs to be in the final answer.
That makes sense.
Um, and if some that's something you
wanna see future videos on, let me know.
I can try to make a practice
problem video on it now.
So dimensional analysis is,
Kind of with Bill Nye right?
Ending with that, who's one of
the best scientists out there
when it comes to teaching camp,
teaching all, all the science.
It's right when the units cancel.
It's, it is simple as that.
That's not a direct quote, but it's
all about just canceling the units.
Let the units guide you, and
I hope this video helped.
We'll try to make more of these math
videos in the future and please hit
that like and subscribe button, help
support the channel and help it grow.
It's been growing and thank you so
much for all, for all that support.
I'll see y'all next time.
This has been Dr.
Dan and I will see you later.